It's an incredible story
and one that's remained secret for over
half a century.
The power of the atom was hardly
understood yet, but it was already a
weapon of total destruction.
This was the Cold War, a merciless
confrontation between East and West with
an ever-growing arsenal of death.
Between 1950 and 1968, hundreds of
nuclear bombs were being transported all
over the planet.
There were a lot of accidents. In
military code, they called them broken
arrows.
And they took the human race to the
brink of apocalypse.
A cloak of silence has been thrown
around those perilous years.
But now the military archives are open
and all the missing bombs of the Cold
War are finally exploding into sight.
February 15th, 1950. The brand new B-36,
the biggest bomber ever made, is getting
ready for takeoff on a secret mission.
On board, a 5-ton nuclear bomb.
It's twice as powerful as the one
dropped on Hiroshima.
>> [snorts]
>> The plane's overloaded and has trouble
reaching its cruising altitude.
Night falls and it's getting cold.
The hours pass. Now the plane's [music]
over Canada.
The captain, Harold Berry, is on maximum
alert.
He doesn't know though that his crew's
lives are hanging in the balance.
Suddenly, the air intake of three of the
engines gets clogged up with ice and has
to be cut.
The plane can't stay aloft and there's
nowhere for it to land.
The crash is inevitable.
>> [music]
>> 40 years later, declassified documents
reveal the story of a doomed mission.
And a Canadian researcher discovered
that the bomber was part of a plan for
total nuclear war against the Soviet
Union.
>> I mean, [music] an early plan was
Operation Dropshot. And Dropshot foresaw
SAC immediately in one giant attack
going after 200 targets with 300 atomic
bombs.
>> The official charged with carrying out
this [music] plan was General LeMay, a
determined man convinced that nuclear
war with the Soviet Union was
inevitable.
>> All of you know that we must be ready to
launch at once our attack in great
force.
We carry a great responsibility
>> Air crews were being mobilized day and
night. Strategists were constantly
revising the list of priority
objectives.
Targets [music] included the enemy's
major cities, military airfields, and
main industrial centers.
Pilots [music] had to know their targets
by heart, and training flights were
being carried out in conditions as close
as possible to actual missions.
Wing Commander Berry and his crew's
mission was one of the most secret of
all.
To reach their objective, they had to
head south first along the coast of
Canada, then the United States.
>> After about 17 hours, they were supposed
to mock drop their bomb over the city of
San Francisco. San Francisco was a
favorite test target for the United
States Air Force because it was supposed
to mimic Leningrad in the Soviet Union.
>> This annihilation [music]
plan by the Americans showed the true
measure of their fear and hatred of the
people they called the Reds.
This was a [music] time when the
communist flag was flying over the whole
of Eastern Europe. For the United
States, the grip that Moscow had on
these nations was very worrying. They
feared the contagion would spread.
Especially since by 1950, the Soviets
also had the atom bomb, and the risk of
nuclear conflict was very real.
>> [cheering]
>> It had all begun at the end of the
Second World War in July 1945 at
Potsdam, where President Harry [music]
Truman met with the other leaders who
had crushed the Nazis.
>> [cheering]
>> His intention was to curb the ambitions
of Joseph Stalin, the president of the
USSR, who was counting on his 5 million
troops to ensure that communism would
hold sway over Europe.
For the time being, though, the allies
had to decide the fate of a Germany torn
between the two blocks and above all
find a way to end the war that still
dragged on in the Pacific.
In his standoff with Stalin, Truman was
holding the trump card.
On the eve of the conference, the first
US nuclear test in the deserts of New
Mexico had been a success, and he was
determined to use his new weapon to
bring Japan to surrender.
On August 6th at Hiroshima and then at
Nagasaki on August 9th, the United
States proved their mastery of the atom
and their willingness to use it.
The world gazed with dread on the face
of the apocalypse.
The devastation caused by the bomb and
by its merciless radiation looked like
divine punishment.
And the few doctors there on the spot
were powerless to help all the wounded.
>> Harry Truman realized that he had just
killed between 2 and 300,000 people. And
he constantly said afterwards
that I never lost a moment's of sleep
over the decision to drop the bomb.
The fact that he said it so often
to me suggests that it may not have been
true.
So, I think that he understood that
these weapons are different.
That they were going to be
indiscriminately killing people in a
wide area.
And so, Truman himself started the
process by which the American president
had control over the weapons.
>> On August 1st, 1946, the Atomic Energy
Act gave birth to a new organization.
>> That was I think very [music] important
because it created the Atomic Energy
Commission and it meant that initially
the weapons were not in the direct
control of the US military. They're
controlled by civilians.
>> The Atomic Energy Commission that had
the expertise to design and build them,
they would build the weapons and then
they would hold the weapons, physically
hold maintain custody,
and only under presidential order in a
crisis or as the country was moving to
war, would they transfer custody of the
weapon
to the military.
>> But right after the war, all those bombs
that were supposed to keep both America
and the free world safe didn't really
exist [music] or at least were still
just prototypes and very complicated to
use.
>> It took a team of
36 men maybe 2 weeks to fully assemble
one.
>> To hold on to its technological lead
over its implacable enemy, America set
its engineers to work to come up with
bombs that were more stable and easier
to produce and use.
>> It was a very expensive process
to develop these weapons, basically,
because
they drew personnel from literally all
over the world
in place to design these.
And it was a
a rush process.
The Mark 4 was
uh the first weapon that was
mass-produced.
And it weighed about 10,000 lb, still 5
ft in diameter and about 10 ft long.
>> By 1949, almost 300 weapons were ready
for use.
Their nuclear payload, though, was
stocked separately and kept under heavy
guard.
Only in a state of alert would the
warhead be placed in the bomb to arm it.
It was a protocol to ensure security, as
well as being an efficient means of
control.
But suddenly one day, Stalin put the cat
among the American pigeons.
On August 29th, 1949, 4 years after the
United States, the Soviet Union carried
out its own nuclear test.
>> The estimate was that it was going to be
10 years at least before the Russians
would have an atomic bomb, and so that
surprised us.
>> For Washington, it was a real wake-up
call.
The general commotion it stirred up
allowed General LeMay to demand that
Truman let him load live atom bombs onto
his bomber planes. And that's how, on
February 15th, 1950, a nuclear weapon
was placed in the hold of Commander
Barry's B-36 for its top-secret mission.
A few hours later, high over the
mountains of British Columbia, the
impossible happened.
One by one, [music] three of its engines
failed.
The plane started losing height. It was
going to crash.
Its captain received an order of the
highest gravity.
>> Before they bailed out, though, they
dropped the atomic bomb over the sea,
and it was fused to detonate above the
surface of the ocean. It did so. It was
witnessed by crew, and it is in the
records that it did detonate.
>> These documents show that for this
training mission, the bomb was not
fitted with a nuclear charge.
Despite its engines being down,
Commander Barry managed at the last
moment to get over dry land and give the
order to abandon the plane.
One minute later, it disappeared from
the radar.
Five men lost their lives in the
accident.
The 12 who survived landed on Princess
Royal Island to the north of Vancouver
in Canada.
30 boats and 40 planes were mobilized to
try to rescue them.
>> In the Arctic winter conditions,
>> [music]
>> it was indeed miraculous that they were
saved.
>> [music]
>> A happy ending, and all America
rejoiced.
>> [music]
>> Meanwhile, General LeMay was furious.
He'd lost men and a plane, but above
all, he was going to have to account for
the lost bomb to the Atomic Energy
Commission.
He decided to keep quiet about it, and
so the papers were all full of the
rescue of the crew with not a single
word about what the plane was carrying.
>> So, when the Atomic Energy Commission
learned from newspapers that an atomic
bomber had been lost over British
Columbia and the crew rescued, they
immediately phoned the US Air Force and
said, [music]
"Is that the bomber with our atomic bomb
on board?" The US Air Force wouldn't
tell them at first. This went on for
several days, and it produced more and
more unhappiness by the Atomic Energy
Commission and by the senators
overseeing this very precious and very
secret [music] weapon.
>> In fact, the military did cover it up
for a number of years after [music] the
loss of the weapon,
mostly because of the
secrecy around the atomic bomb,
but also because
it occurred
on foreign territory,
over Canada.
>> After a few weeks, the military,
convinced that the aircraft must have
broken up at sea, gave up the search.
But the story of the B-36 wasn't over
yet. 4 years later, in 1954, the
Canadian Air Force announced that they'd
found the plane in a far-flung corner of
the country.
The US Air Force mounted a desperate
search to reach the wreck at any price,
and a secret commando force at last got
to it after a year of trying. Not a
single declassified document gives any
explanation for their dogged
persistence.
Half a century later, in 2003, a
Canadian team led by John Clearwater
managed to get to the site.
What they found there was extraordinary.
The whole fuselage of the bomber had
been crushed to bits.
And they also found crates of
explosives.
The plane had obviously been blown to
bits in a methodical manner. A
professional job that could only have
been the work of those commandos.
>> The mission was to destroy a very secret
bomber lest it fall into the hands of
Soviet spies who decided to climb the
mountain and to destroy evidence of the
secret equipment,
the aircraft engines, whatever allowed
that airplane to be the most
technologically advanced bomber on the
planet at the time.
>> If it wasn't for the determination of
John Clearwater, history's very first
nuclear accident, the first broken
arrow, would never have gone public.
In 1950, General LeMay believed the lost
bomb should remain a state secret.
It was essential not to show any
weakness to the Soviets, who had just
developed their own nuclear bomb.
The United States was afraid,
and the communists were gaining ground.
One year earlier, Mao Zedong had
proclaimed the People's Republic of
China, a single-party state with a
collectivist agenda.
Now, 70% of Asia was under communist
rule.
Mao's victory was an inspiration to the
guerrillas of Indonesia and the
Philippines, and especially French
Indonesia, where the battle had already
been raging for 3 years now.
But it was in Korea, split in two at the
end of the Second World War, that the
confrontation between the two camps was
to burst into flame.
At dawn on June 24th, 1950, the North
Korean communist leader Kim Il-sung
invaded South Korea.
The South Korean army was routed, and
the population fled.
General MacArthur, at the head of an
international coalition force of 200,000
men set up by the UN, landed in Korea.
He managed to drive the Reds back to the
Chinese border.
But the victory was a brief one.
The Chinese, feeling threatened, mounted
a counteroffensive and pushed back the
coalition forces.
>> [music]
>> MacArthur wanted to take back North
Korea with nuclear weapons.
Truman wouldn't let him.
>> I believe that we must try to limit the
war to Korea and to prevent a third
world war.
A number of events have made it evident
that General MacArthur did not agree
with that policy.
I have therefore considered it essential
to relieve General MacArthur
so that there would be no doubt or
confusion as to the real purpose and aim
of our policy.
>> A demilitarized zone was set up along
the border and the two camps began a
long face-off.
Truman, the only man ever to have used a
nuclear weapon, didn't wish to repeat
the experience.
Things were very tense for a while, but
he stood up to the military and avoided
things escalating.
His successor, Dwight Eisenhower,
changed everything.
The former commander-in-chief of Allied
Forces in Europe had the trust of the
military and in matters of defense, they
saw eye-to-eye.
>> President Eisenhower, famously a
five-star general, had a long tradition
as a military officer before he became
president and so was willing to
uh see things through military eyes in a
way that some other uh civilian
presidents were unwilling to do.
>> Eisenhower had learned his lesson in the
Korean War. Never again would he give up
a single inch of land to the communists.
But he still had to get Congress to vote
for an increased military budget.
>> To continue over the years just ahead to
maintain the Strategic Air Command in
the state of maximum safety, strength,
and alert
as new kinds of threats develop
will entail additional costs.
>> [applause]
>> The Americans had to hold on to their
lead, so they accelerated their military
nuclear program.
In November 1952, the first prototype of
the H-bomb, a hundred times more
powerful than the previous A-bomb, was
secretly tested in the Pacific.
The energy released by this 23-ft, 6-ton
monster was a hundred times that of the
Hiroshima bomb.
>> 3
>> The death of Stalin on March 5th, 1953
had no impact, however, on Soviet
scientists' race to catch up.
And 5 months later in the deserts of
Kazakhstan
the first Soviet H-bomb exploded.
This near immediate response put the
United States in a frenzy.
The whole time bomb drills were
preparing people for the worst.
>> The Applejack alert. Enemy bombers in
theory are approaching the world's
greatest city.
While the sirens wail their grim
warning, hundreds of thousands of New
Yorkers scurry for shelter against the
attack for a day all Americans pray will
never come.
>> In an instant, the deserted streets were
all haunted by the spectre of nuclear
holocaust.
They were on training missions all the
time now. They were training thousands
of pilots and technicians and moving
hundreds of nuclear bombs around the
country.
And that's when Nikita Khrushchev,
hitherto more or less unknown in the
West, became first secretary of the
Communist Party of the Soviet Union.
More than ever now, President Eisenhower
doubted the intentions of his adversary,
especially in Europe. 10 years after the
war had ended, the fate of Berlin was
still not settled. [music]
Since 1949, Germany had been cut in two
and Berlin was still occupied by the
Americans and their allies.
Khrushchev described Berlin as a
cancerous tumor in the middle of the
East Germany.
He would soon demand that all Westerners
leave. The two blocks were heading for a
clash.
In 1957, at NATO's first-ever summit, 11
Western European countries confirmed
their alliance with the United States,
which they saw as the only barrier to
Soviet expansionism.
>> Air defense. This is General Turner, air
defense command.
>> That's when America deployed its bombs
in Europe. And it was while transporting
one of them that another accident
occurred.
On March 11th, 1958, a squadron of B-47s
was preparing to take off for Europe.
These were the new bombers with jet
engines instead of propellers and with a
top speed of over 600 miles an hour.
They could be flown by a crew of just
three.
Each of those crews only had 1 hour to
load a 3.5 ton Mark 6 nuclear bomb onto
its plane.
Sergeant Gary Coe was in charge of
loading.
>> I was 22, 23 year old sergeant.
We were under a lot of pressure because
we had a limited time that we had to get
the aircraft ready for
so the flight crews could get them ready
to fly.
This was the real thing. It was no
exercise. We did this every month with
four, six, or eight aircraft that we
rotated back and forth to Europe to be
on alert.
We were at war.
Even though it was a cold war,
we had to deter the Russians.
Khrushchev said he would bury us.
And we had to make sure that he didn't.
>> The crew of three that was off to
England knew their aircraft very well.
It had a very heavy load, but took off
with no problem.
>> But at an altitude of 5,000 ft, a
warning light signaled a problem with
the pin that held the bomb in place.
>> The pilot
required the bombardier to go back in
the bomb bay and check the pin.
In the process of him trying to check
the pin
is when he lost his balance and grabbed
the emergency release cable
and it released the hook
and the bomb dropped through the bomb
bay doors
for just a second or two and then it
went on out the bomb bay doors.
And he struggled to keep a hold of
something in the bomb bay so he could
get back up into the aircraft through
the crawl crawl way.
He was lucky.
He almost went with it.
>> The distraught crew had to report the
release of the bomb and its detonation
in anguish at the thought of its
possible victims.
Immediately back at Strategic Air
Command, the nuclear accident alarm rang
out.
The bomb detonated just outside the
village of Mars Bluff in South Carolina.
People there were panicked and the local
authorities rushed to the scene.
The 2 and 1/2 tons of explosives packed
around the device had left a crater 30
ft deep.
It was a unique historical event that
would mark this little rural community
forever.
60 years later, this fragment of the
bomb that fell on Mars Bluff is one of
the main attractions at the museum in
the neighboring town of Florence.
Over the years, its curator, Steven
Mott, with his keen interest in this
extraordinary accident, has assembled
hundreds of documents about it.
>> In the beginning, there was a lot of
confusion
when the bomb
exploded.
People didn't know what had happened.
When that story
was released and people knew that it was
a bomb,
then there was fear about
contamination from radioactive
components.
>> Checks were carried out to ensure there
was no radioactivity, but the military
were careful to collect every little
piece of the huge and top-secret
munition.
A commission of inquiry questioned the
plane's crew.
A declassified document shows that no
charges were brought against them.
But this accident, right there in a
little village, was impossible to keep
quiet.
The military had sealed off the site,
but under pressure from the media, they
were forced to grant access, and the
press all rushed to the scene.
>> [music]
>> An atomic bomb breaks loose from a
mounting shackle in a B-47 jet over
Florence, South Carolina, plummets to
earth, causing a sensational freak
accident. There was near disaster for
those within range of the TNT, [music]
that is the bomb's trigger. Six were
injured. The home of Walter Gregg was
turned into a shambles.
>> Once again, fortunately, the bomb had no
nuclear charge, just an enormous load of
explosives.
For the Gregg family, it was a painful
ordeal.
Helen was six at the time.
>> We'd gone to church, it was a Sunday.
And my sister
>> [music]
>> and myself, we were playing in the side
yard and
uh all of a sudden we just the the
ground started shaking.
And stuff started hitting us in the head
and all and we just dropped to the
ground and covered our head up and
I was fine. My sister was fine and my
brother was fine.
We were kind of shook up, but we were
fine.
>> [music]
>> My father was hurt some.
My first cousin, she was hurt and my
mother was hurt worst. She was in a to
the hospital.
We had a cat
and the luckily the cat made it.
>> [music]
>> She went behind the refrigerator and hid
in the back of the refrigerator. So
nothing fell on top of her.
>> I've got a secret.
>> The Greggs went on a popular TV quiz
show where celebrity panelists had to
guess what had happened to them.
>> Did it [clears throat] happen here in
New York?
>> No.
>> You are from the South, aren't you?
>> Yes.
>> Yes, did it happen back home?
>> At home.
>> At home, did it happen in your house?
>> Partially.
>> This is the family from Florence, South
Carolina, who miraculously escaped
injury when their house was hit by an
atom bomb on March 11th.
>> [applause]
>> What is What's viewpoint toward that,
sir? Do feel resentment?
>> Are you angry about it?
>> No. I think uh bombs are a good thing to
have. Just use them at proper places.
>> [applause]
>> The Gregg family had their moment of
fame, but in fact, they were living a
nightmare.
>> We lost everything. We had We The only
thing we had was the clothes on our
back.
>> When it came to compensation, the
military bitterly contested the damages.
>> The Gregg family expected
fair compensation.
They expected
that there would be more sympathy
from the Air Force.
And I think that Walter Gregg,
especially, felt betrayed as time went
on because he was
a member of the Air Force. He He was a
military veteran.
>> 50 years later, you can still visit the
bomb site.
Back at the scene of her childhood,
Helen Gregg remembers.
The family home's long gone.
Around the crater, which is slowly
filling in now, the forest has grown
back. However, if the bomb had been
armed, it would have wiped a whole
village off the map and contaminated the
whole of South Carolina.
At the time, the accident at Mars Bluff
was just another news item. The America
of the late '50s wasn't exactly up in
arms. Everyone still had complete faith
in the armed forces.
But in England, where the Mars Bluff
bomb had been heading, people were
scared of the American bombers.
Hundreds were protesting against the
nuclear tests and against having US
bombs on British soil. Public awareness
was growing.
>> [cheering]
>> And those peace marchers had good reason
to be worried.
In just a few years, America's stock of
nuclear weapons had increased 10-fold to
18,600 by 1960, 10 times more than the
USSR.
On October 4th, 1957, a metal ball
prickling with antennas had hit all the
headlines.
The launch of Sputnik, the very first
satellite, had come as a bolt from the
blue for the US.
>> The Russians were now capable of putting
a missile and and a
and a satellite into outer space, and
this was well beyond anything the United
States could do at the time.
>> If the Soviets could launch a satellite,
they could fire an intercontinental
nuclear missile.
Suddenly, America was no longer an
impregnable fortress. Khrushchev had
thrown down the gauntlet.
For the increasingly worried US
military, it was vital to have precise
knowledge of its adversary's forces.
On May 1st, 1960, an American spy plane
was shot down over Soviet territory
while photographing military objectives.
The United States fiercely denied
everything, but Khrushchev had proof,
and he accused Eisenhower of lying.
But, Strategic Air Command continued its
irresistible rise.
Its budget was now bigger than Standard
Oil's, the biggest company in the world
at the time.
A new underground command center was
opened in Nebraska, from which they
could track [music] in real time the
position of as many as 2,500 fighter
planes.
>> [music]
>> And the command now had a new type of
plane, the B-52, a bomber whose range of
nearly 9,000 mi gave it access to the
whole Soviet territory.
At this point, General LeMay was
replaced at the head of the US Air Force
by General Thomas Power.
He was every bit as ruthless and
determined as his predecessor. Power was
very demanding of his men, and obsessed
with reducing at all costs their
reaction time to any attack.
His first priority was to get those
bombs armed much more quickly.
Up till then, the nuclear payload had
been separate and inserted at the last
moment.
>> And this uh
what made sense until [music]
the Soviets developed uh missile
capability, which reduced the warning
time down to minutes. At that point, you
might not have enough time to
>> [music]
>> transfer the nuclear uh component and
assemble it on site, and
uh get the uh the airplane aloft. And
so,
the uh at this
>> [music]
>> they moved to a a different system which
had the weapons fully assembled, ready
to go.
>> The engineers found a solution. They
embedded the nuclear core in the bomb at
the factory, meaning zero delay arming
the bomb. It was ready.
And the planes had to be as well.
Power saw to it that all his bombers
were ready for takeoff in less than 15
minutes.
But still, that wasn't enough. He had a
certain number, kept top secret, of
armed bombers constantly in flight.
Little did Americans know that there
were always nuclear bombs right over
their heads.
And that's how on January 24th, 1961, a
B-52 took off on a 23-hour mission. In
its hold, two bombs with a destructive
power 250 times that of the Hiroshima
bomb.
And it wasn't just an exercise. Every
flight now could result in a nuclear
strike on the Soviet Union.
>> I was living in that white house right
down there.
And and I heard this awful noise. I had
just come home from work. I looked out
my window
>> [music]
>> and I saw my room was like a blaze.
I heard my mama praying and I jumped up
and and [music] and my daddy was getting
his clothes on and I saw the plane as it
was twirling like this in the air.
The trees were on fire over here.
In 45 minutes time, when the plane hit
the ground,
Air Force was out here.
They would come up big
>> [music]
>> a flying I've seen more Johnson
helicopter with a huge spotlight saying
evacuate, evacuate, evacuate, evacuate,
and we did.
>> It's a closely guarded secret that was
only brought to light by Strategic Air
Command officer Joel Dobson after more
than 10 years of searching through
thousands of classified documents.
>> It's one of the few uh
accidents where all evidence of the
crash is completely gone, and began to
investigate by talking to the people on
the scene. And the amazing thing was
they were told uh even though they lived
in the same area for 50 years, they were
told they were never to speak of it. So,
it was highly secretive at the time.
>> On the morning of January 23rd, 1961, an
aircraft uh piloted by Major Scott
Tulloch took off from Goldsboro, North
Carolina performing a exercise, a actual
airborne alert.
>> The mission was going smoothly until
suddenly the co-pilot reported a fuel
leak from the starboard engine. There
was a tear in it visibly growing bigger.
They requested an emergency landing at
Goldsboro base.
>> I was an EOD man, 24 year old, on
standby on January the 24th, 1961, when
I got a call around midnight from the
control tower telling me that B-52
bomber in trouble had uh fuel leaks in
the bomb bay area.
I grabbed up my clothes and I headed out
for the base and it was a real cold cold
January night.
>> They lost the 19 tons of fuel
uh and almost immediately, there had to
be a massive rupture somewhere within
the wing.
The wing was called the wet wing because
it carried uh fuel tanks in the wing
itself.
>> Position 051015.
Odell Alston, 21.
>> The situation was turning critical. The
commander, Major Tulloch, knew he had
just one slim chance of landing.
Then the plane was shaken by a huge
crack.
>> The airplane broke apart in midair. The
wing had broken [music] off, the tail
had
broken off, nose was down, but it was
spinning.
>> Five of the crew ejected. A sixth jumped
with his parachute.
Two stayed stuck on the plane.
At half past midnight, [music] the plane
crashed into a field near Goldsboro.
Three men would not survive the crash.
>> This is a picture
of where they're removing Major
Shelton's body from there.
>> [snorts]
>> And I, as a young man, I had never
smelled
the smell of burning flesh.
And it was absolutely horrific.
>> A helicopter was sent to search for the
two bombs. A big surprise awaited.
>> And they he turned the light on the uh
the chopper and it showed the first bomb
with the parachute.
>> It was sticking up from the ground like
a huge totem pole.
>> I always wore a little pouch on my side
that had tools and I chipped around and
got the access door open
where I seen that the arm safe switch
was on safe.
So, it wasn't a big worry on that at the
time.
>> The US Air Force combed the whole area,
but they couldn't find the second bomb.
Joe Dobson came across the name of
someone who'd played a key role back
[music] on that day.
>> So, this document was how I first
discovered the name of Jack ReVelle,
first lieutenant. He was the commander
of the explosive ordnance disposal team
at at Wright-Patterson Air Force Base,
Ohio.
>> For 50 years, this man had been bound by
military secret and wasn't allowed to
say anything.
Today, though, he wants to tell his
incredible story.
>> Somewhere early in the morning
5:00, 5:30 a.m.
on January 24th, 1961
I received a a call. I was sound asleep
in my bed.
I received a call from my boss.
And it instead of using the code words
that we had rehearsed he said to me,
"Jack
I've got a real one for you."
>> Jack ReVelle jumped into a jet. In just
a few hours, he was at the crash site.
A rapid inquiry and he was able to piece
together what happened and direct the
search. The second bomb was under the
ground.
>> Parachute did not deploy.
And as a direct result
when the bomb come came penetrate came
down and penetrated the ground about the
speed of sound. Skin of [music] the
weapon began to peel away from the
friction
of the earth that it that it was passing
through.
>> There, 20 ft deep,
was the smashed-up bomb with its nuclear
charge sticking out.
The mine clearer, Earl Smith, called up
to Revell.
>> Hey, Lieutenant, we found the arm safe
switch.
And I said, "Great." And he says, "No,
not great. It's on arm."
And it got very quiet.
Because we were concerned, you know, you
know, is this thing going to blow?
>> Earl Smith tried to find the most
dangerous part of the bomb, its nuclear
core.
>> Then I got in the bottom of the hole.
And everything I'm feeling around to
different parts to describe what and
then I feel the the ball the core
eventually and pull it up between my
legs and hand it to somebody. I don't
know might have been Lieutenant Revell,
might have been one of his men,
somebody.
>> I reached [music] down
and I picked up this approximately 20-lb
nuclear sphere,
brought it up to my chest like [music]
this,
and walked over to the ladder, the
wooden ladder,
and began to climb raising myself up
from the 18 ft to the surface [music] of
the ground.
>> Mission accomplished. And for the team,
a huge relief.
>> If either bomb,
or even worse, both bombs [music]
had detonated, you'd have a 3.8 megaton
explosion.
That's 3.8 million tons of TNT
equivalent.
And you'd have a a hole with 100% kill
uh 70 mi across diameter where you have
nothing, just a big hole in the ground.
Probably ended up with either a gulf or
a bay of North Carolina, but it [music]
would completely reconfigure the
landscape of the eastern seaboard of the
United States.
>> The apocalypse didn't happen, but the
lower part of the bomb, which also
contained highly radioactive elements,
remained buried nearly 200 ft deep.
For 4 months, they kept digging, but in
the end, the US Air Force threw in the
towel.
>> There's another document that a lot of
it was restricted, as you can see.
One interesting sentence is
in any case, it is considered advice of
the Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory
that some water samples be taken for
analysis and the hole be filled up and
forgotten.
>> Here underground, a part of the nuclear
core of America's most powerful bomb of
its day still lies sleeping.
It could contain several pounds of
plutonium 239, one of the most toxic
substances in the world.
However, at the time, the accident at
Goldsboro didn't cause much of a stir.
Day after day, the B-52 missions carried
on as usual.
On January 20th, 1961, a new young
president of America took office. John
Fitzgerald Kennedy would face some major
crises.
The wall being built in Berlin was a
very real iron curtain between two
[music] worlds.
The United States was deploying a
nuclear arsenal in Europe that directly
threatened the Soviet Union.
Khrushchev replied by installing
missiles in Cuba, only 120 miles from
the Florida coast.
These crises led to new, even more
destructive arms being deployed.
And fresh accidents occurred on a scale
never seen before.
In the south of Spain, a peaceful
village was contaminated forever.
And in the ice fields of Greenland, a
B-52 crashed with four nuclear bombs on
board.
The arsenal of death, capable of
destroying the planet several times
over, continued to grow inexorably.
The Cold War was leading humanity
towards catastrophe.
But for now, Americans would rather not
think about that.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The full story of the face-off between
the Soviet Union and the United States
after the Second World War has remained
secret for more than half a century.
This was the Cold War, when two
superpowers both had atomic bombs and
were threatening each other with total
destruction.
Dozens of nuclear accidents, they called
them broken arrows, had resulted from
the deployment of that dreadful weapon.
Through censorship and reasons of state,
those sensitive dossiers were all
repressed. But now declassified
documents can reveal the facts about
those catastrophes that led humankind to
the brink of apocalypse, and the lost
bombs of the Cold War are finally
exploding into sight.
On August 6th, 1945, the bomber Enola
Gay dropped the atom bomb they called
Little Boy on Hiroshima.
And the world entered the nuclear age.
President Harry Truman had provided
devastating proof of American power.
He'd brought Japan to its knees and
fired off a warning to Stalin, whose
expansionist aims were becoming
troublesome.
The USSR had millions of troops and
thousands of tanks. Since the end of the
war, the Red Army had been only
partially demobilized.
>> [cheering]
>> Truman was counting on fear of the bomb
that he alone possessed to hold them in
check.
He kept on testing more and more bombs
and urging his engineers to turn the
prototypes into real mass-produced
weapons.
>> [music]
>> But then, the first Soviet nuclear test
took America by surprise.
And thus began the mad race for nuclear
supremacy.
The first American hydrogen bomb went
off in the Pacific on the Marshall
Islands.
It was 100 times more powerful than the
one at Hiroshima.
Nine months later, the Soviets had their
own.
And the race was on.
The Americans tested Castle Bravo, a
bomb 150 times more powerful than
Hiroshima.
Khrushchev's response, the Bomba, was a
monster, three times again more
powerful. The terrifying escalation had
reached its peak.
>> Mutual assured destruction
was a doctrine that both the United
States and the Soviet Union operated
under that
we could maintain peace as long as each
side was vulnerable to an attack from an
from the other side. So, they were both
assured of destroying one another so
they wouldn't have any incentive to
launch the first strike.
>> But, this was a strategy that placed
American bomber crews under intolerable
pressure.
>> We asked the US military during the Cold
War to do the impossible.
Be ready
to launch nuclear weapons on a moment's
notice
and never ever have an accident.
That's impossible.
We shouldn't have been asking the US
military to do that.
So, to me
the lesson of this is that going on
nuclear alerts
that's inherently dangerous. It's very
risky.
>> Since the end of the war, there had
already been 28 nuclear accidents,
fortunately without any contamination.
Mars Bluff in South Carolina, Goldsboro
in North Carolina, Yuba in California.
The risk was at its height in 1966 when
the government insisted that American
bombers should be permanently in the air
and on high alert.
>> We start flying routinely
B-52 bombers with thermonuclear weapons
on board. And we did that because
Strategic Air Command believed that if
there was a surprise attack by the
Soviet Union on the United States, the
bombers on the ground might get
destroyed.
And for the sake of deterrence, they
wanted to have some weapons in the air
all the time.
>> Thus it was that on January 17th, 1966,
at a base in North Carolina, four
nuclear bombs were loaded onto a bomber
plane [music] for a 24-hour mission.
Captain Windorf and Major Messinger knew
they might at any moment receive the
order to drop their dreadful load.
It was a show of strength in which the
pilots were true American heroes.
>> [music]
>> The plane would cross the Atlantic, fly
over the Mediterranean, and head up to
the very edge of the Communist block to
be in position for a nuclear
retaliation.
On the return flight, they had to refuel
in flight over Spain.
At 30,000 ft, approach maneuvers to a
tanker aircraft are tricky. The
slightest error can prove fatal.
The telescopic boom was deployed to
transfer the 13,000 gallons of highly
inflammable jet fuel.
But there was turbulence, and it all
went wrong.
degrees.
Roger, moving left.
20 degrees elevation.
Break away. BREAK AWAY.
>> THE TANKER AIRCRAFT EXPLODED, killing
all four crew members.
The bomber was badly damaged and span
out of control.
Four of the crew managed to eject.
The nuclear bombs were expelled from the
hold.
>> [music]
>> And the plane crashed near the village
of Palomares on the Andalusian coast.
A reporter, Rafael Martinez [music]
Durban, was among the first at the scene
of the crash, where three bodies were
found.
>> People were already there from the
village.
And my first impression,
I don't know what upset me more.
The sight or the smell.
It was a mixture of jet fuel,
rubber,
smoke,
and burnt flesh.
The undercarriage had landed just yards
from a school where 20 or more children
were at their lessons.
It's a miracle they were all right.
Four members of the B-52 crew survived
and were looked after by the locals.
It was the first nuclear accident on
European soil.
A few hours later, the arrival of US Air
Force mine clearance teams caused quite
a stir.
They'd never seen a helicopter before in
Palomares.
The teams immediately started searching
for the four bombs and were astonished
[music] not to find them there in the
wreck.
With help from the locals, they found
three of them scattered here and there
in the village.
These declassified photos show that the
first had landed in a dry riverbed,
apparently intact thanks to its
parachute.
But that wasn't the case with the two
others.
>> Two of those weapons,
the parachute did not deploy on.
So, when the weapons impacted the
ground,
the 300 lb of high explosive in those
weapons exploded, scattering the active
material
over the area.
>> This extraordinary footage shows the
mine clearers recuperating fragments of
the bombs.
There was no nuclear explosion, but the
bombs had released a large quantity of
plutonium and the contamination was
enormous.
As for the fourth, it was nowhere to be
found.
And that immediately put things on the
highest alert.
>> Uh we had a few takeoffs.
>> For the US Air Force, it was vital not
to drop their guard and let the Soviets
take advantage of this accident. The
government decided to continue its
deterrent overflights.
>> 24 hours after the accident, the
Americans bomber is starting again
overflying Spain with nuclear arms. And
some point someone in the Franco regime
said, "Okay, that's absolutely crazy.
No, we still won't We don't know what is
happening. So, on a state we have other
nuclear armaments overflying Spain. So,
they request officially to cancel
overflights with nuclear armament over
Spain.
>> President Johnson was unhappy about this
and tried his best to change Franco's
mind.
Their two countries were bound by a 1953
agreement. American forces had paid one
and a half billion dollars to be allowed
to install five military bases in Spain.
Since they were halfway to the Soviet
Union, they were strategically useful
when it came to nuclear deterrence.
They were home to 12,000 GIs in a
permanent [music] state of alert.
Two of those bases immediately sent 300
soldiers to Palomares.
>> In the afternoon
the buses full of soldiers arrived.
>> We knew they were Americans because they
were all black.
>> We'd never seen a person of color
before.
>> The men were sent straight off to search
for the missing bomb.
They could at any point have been
exposed to radioactive debris, but they
wore no protection.
But wherever they went, the Geiger
counters went crazy.
The contamination from the bombs had
formed two long parallel corridors.
They covered an area equivalent to 200
football fields.
Here in this region, there are strong
southeast winds, and they spread the
radioactive dust.
And this was an inhabited area with
crops, too. Urgent action was called
for.
And the first thing was to stop any more
of the dust from spreading.
The local people still had no idea how
serious the situation was.
>> Later, they came around with this device
for the radioactivity.
I had this little window at the back,
and they put this thing there, and it
was full of radioactivity.
They didn't say anything about bombs.
They just said not to touch anything and
not to go out at all, but everyone was
already outside to find out what was
going on.
>> I didn't know it was a nuclear bomb.
I just didn't know.
We didn't know much back then about
nuclear bombs.
>> After 5 days spent systematically
searching the whole area, the military
realized that the bomb must have fallen
in the sea.
The United States Sixth Fleet was
stationed in the Mediterranean, so was
ordered to locate and recover it as
quickly as possible. It must not fall
into foreign hands.
The stunned residents of Palomares were
experiencing all the power of Uncle Sam,
and they have never forgotten it.
>> All of the tools they brought
the sheer cost of it, the equipment they
had.
You just can't imagine.
It was incredible.
>> Within days, a military camp had been
set up on the beach at Palomares.
Commando teams of divers were combing
the whole coast.
And state-of-the-art US submarines had
been called in to search the open sea.
>> [music]
>> However, all of this activity ended up
catching the attention of the press.
>> So, one of the first decisions that the
the Americans and the Spaniards decided
took was don't close completely the
area. They don't evacuate the area.
So, that allowed also for the
journalists to come to the area and then
talk to the people.
>> In Palomares, there were reporters
everywhere.
They were interviewing people and
talking to witnesses.
It wouldn't take them long to find out
things the military would rather cover
up.
Back in the States, the first to go to
press was The New York Times.
Franco was furious [music]
that he couldn't control this often
sensationalist foreign press coverage.
>> A dozen ships from the American 6th
Fleet are now helping the Air Force in
the search code-named Operation Broken
Arrow. Cruisers and destroyers with
sonar equipment have been trying to
locate the lost bomb and also screening
the approaches against enemy spies.
Spanish Civil Guards and secret police
cordoned the area around the American
camp in Palomares, but Colonel Skip
Young, the information officer, wouldn't
even admit there was an H-bomb missing.
No comment was as talkative as he would
get.
>> Also that the Soviets used the Palomares
incident to criticize United States and
Spanish and Franco regime.
>> And the propaganda went wild
with images like this of an arrogant
American officer leaving a trail of
death.
But this was the Cold War and no holds
were barred. So the Soviets incited
Western European communists to protect
against the dangers of imperialism and
more and more concerned citizens were
joining in.
>> At Palomares, it was a publicity
nightmare for the Air Force.
They
they released what had happened. The Air
Force tried to get rid of the problem as
quickly as they could.
>> The decontamination operation began.
The crops were all covered in
radioactive fallout. They had to be
destroyed.
People in Palomares made their living
from tomatoes and overnight they lost
their livelihood.
Their crops had all become nuclear
waste.
The military's method for getting rid of
them was simple but not a particularly
good idea.
>> You can't burn something that's
radioactive because if you do, the smoke
becomes radioactive
and you create another problem all
together.
>> This declassified footage gives a
glimpse behind the scenes of the huge
clear-up.
They'd given up on the burning now.
All the plants were thrown into
specially made drums.
But then there was the soil itself. It
too was contaminated.
The sheer volume of it was enormous.
They'd already used thousands of drums.
The US government was getting worried
about the expense of it all and trying
to limit the cost.
>> There is clear documents where they
renegotiate between the Spanish and the
Americans and was difficult because was
not so easy on other part of the of the
land so they agree to to let some
contamination there.
>> Eventually, the Spanish agreed to lower
the permitted levels of radioactivity.
That's where the real problems began for
Palomares.
In return, the Americans, who'd been
intending to just leave everything
there, agreed to take all the waste back
to the United States.
Another enormous expense for the
government.
But there was more to it than that.
Professor Moreno has come across a
document that proves that the Americans
deliberately cheated to keep the cost
down.
>> Also, we realized that in some of the
the the places, the only thing they do
was to put the the contamination on the
bottom. They put it on on 1 m deep um
from the surface because they thought
those lands will never will be and you
know removed.
>> When the soil had been turned over, it
no longer set off the Geiger counters.
On the surface, it was all clean.
And its owner even got a certificate of
non-contamination.
But when the land was again cultivated,
the radioactivity was still there. A
veritable time bomb for the future.
But it was the lost bomb that the
Spanish were worried about now. It could
ruin the tourist season, the country's
main source of income.
So the Minister of Information and
Tourism attempted an audacious bit of
public relations.
But it was no use. Everyone was worried
about that radiation and the PR stunt
was a failure. That summer, Palomares
beach was deserted.
That bomb was driving the politicians
mad, but the kids just made fun of it
all while dancing the twist.
>> [music and singing]
[music]
>> Yet, for folks at Palomares, it wasn't
so much fun.
In the eyes of the world, they were like
plague victims, and you could see the
worry on their faces.
So, General Wilson decided to call the
heads of all the families together.
He called for unity against the
communist menace and extolled the
friendship between Spain and America.
The villagers, intimidated, didn't dare
to object.
The meeting didn't solve anything.
>> [music]
>> All they were told was to do what the
authorities said
and not go into the fields.
That was the only advice they were
given.
So, of course, rumors were rife, and
people were getting more anxious by the
hour.
First, the farmers, then the fishermen,
lost their only source of income.
People just didn't want to eat fish.
>> People just didn't want to eat fish.
They said it was contaminated. So the
boats just didn't go out.
So then hunger is a serious
serious hunger.
And those totally peaceful people got
angry and they marched on the military
base because they'd been hungry for over
a week.
>> [cheering]
>> The military realized they'd
underestimated the financial
consequences of the accident on the
villagers. [cheering]
To cut things short,
the Americans bought a part of the local
harvest and used it to feed the troops.
So the men were eating tomatoes with
every meal.
Over the following days, they gave the
poorest villagers odd jobs to [music]
do.
And the soldiers, moved to see the
villagers in such distress, handed out
[music] their own rations to them.
>> [music]
>> All it took to restore peace to
Palomares was a fistful of dollars.
But by early April, despite 80 days of
undersea searching, the fourth bomb
still hadn't been found, and Washington
didn't
Admiral Guest ordered his search teams
to go over their results again to make
sure they hadn't missed anything.
And indeed, one witness had been
overlooked. After the accident, Spanish
police had questioned a fisherman.
While out at sea pulling in [music] his
nets, Simo Ort had seen a strange
parachute off in the distance.
With no hesitation, he out exactly where
in an area that hadn't yet been
searched.
One last chance.
The submarine set off on the hunt just
one more time.
And one last dive into unknown waters,
waters that turned out to be dangerous.
>> [music]
>> A submarine had to descend through a
crumbling gorge where the walls
threatened to bury it at any moment.
Then, suddenly, at a depth of 2,500 ft,
they made out a white shape. It was a
parachute with, still attached [music]
to it, the bomb.
>> [music]
>> They brought it up from the abyss and
onto the deck. It seemed intact,
>> [music]
>> so it hadn't contaminated the sea.
After three long months of searching,
this was a considerable technical
achievement.
>> The 8th of April was Easter.
I think it was Good Friday.
They took us to Garrucha and put us all
in a boat.
They didn't tell us anything.
And we saw a ship pass by with a bomb on
deck.
It was going so slowly that we could
take photos.
Then it disappeared.
>> This press circus was proof that the
mission had been a success.
First the Spanish, then the
international press celebrated a triumph
for the US Navy.
Their work done, the Americans packed
their bags and left the people of
Palomares to grapple with the aftermath
of an event whose consequences they
didn't yet fully understand.
50 years later, the children have all
grown up and the village is a thriving
seaside resort.
But an open wound remains. The
contaminated land, 40 hectares in all,
has never been cleaned up despite
repeated promises from the United
States.
>> Every time I go by there, where the
radiation is so strong,
I feel like I'm getting a dose of it.
I don't think it'll ever go away.
We're absorbing it every day.
So I'm always a bit scared.
All the time.
>> With the accident at Palomares, the US
Air Force lost its right to overfly
Spain, and that put a big dent in its
deterrent capabilities.
A worrying situation for President
Johnson.
Secretary of Defense Robert McNamara
wanted to reduce the number of B-52
warning missions. They were too risky,
too costly, and disastrous for the
United States public image.
But the generals didn't agree.
For 20 years, their bombers had
confronted those Soviet missiles. They
represented all the military might of
America.
And to Leonid Brezhnev, the latest
strongman at the Kremlin, knew his
missiles, the stars of the 1st of May
parades, had enabled the Soviets to face
up to the United States in the Cuba
crisis.
And they were also driving the space
race.
And there too, thanks to the power and
reliability of its rockets, the USSR was
in the lead.
The first satellite and the first man in
space were both communist.
Then in 1967, the Soviets launched a new
intercontinental missile capable of
carrying a nuclear payload over 6,000
miles.
>> American science was way behind. We had
put all of our eggs in the basket of
bombers, flying flying warheads around.
>> America caught up, but its B-52s were
still on the front line.
>> Curtis LeMay, the chief of the Air Force
at the time, [music] said that that
threat required us to go go a much
higher state of alert,
creating a number of
dangers, but we did that in order to try
to reinforce our threat of retaliation.
[music]
>> Pilot, radar, 1/4 mi dead ahead.
>> So, the US Air Force would now stretch
its bombers and their crews to the
limits to concentrate on a region that
was crucial to America's security.
>> Normally, you perceive the Cold War as
an East-West conflict, but when you look
at the Arctic, you and you observe the
the globe from the top,
you will see that the Arctic actually is
in the middle of the the shortest
distance [music] between the United
States and the Soviet Union. So, in the
era of long-distance bombers, the Arctic
was predisposed to play a key role,
actually.
>> The United States had the foresight to
put into place in the far north a huge
warning system all around Alaska,
Canada, and Greenland. A chain of 65
radars that stretched for over 3,000 mi.
The gigantic Thule Air Base on the
Danish island of Greenland had become an
outpost of the Western world, sitting at
the edge of a frozen sea that only
thawed out for 2 months a year.
Its giant radar was running 24 hours a
day, and its sensors could detect a
Soviet missile thousands of miles away.
>> We also knew, however, that it might be
the first
place to be attacked. Cuz one thing you
would do if you were
um the Soviet Union initiating a war is
try to take out American radar.
>> The radar was under surveillance by
bomber flights in relay over the base
both day and night
on a secret mission baptized Thule
monitor.
>> [music]
>> It could report back to the strategic
command that Thule is under attack or
Thule is just not operating and there's
some kind of severing of the
communications line.
>> On January 21st, 1968, the B-52 on duty,
armed with four nuclear bombs, was
tirelessly doing its rounds above the
base at temperatures of minus 40°.
Some of the crew were off duty for a few
hours and complaining of the cold, so
the co-pilot turned up the heating.
That's when the unthinkable happened.
Three cushions that had been left in
front of a heating vent caught fire.
The smell of burning alerted the pilot,
but the fire had spread rapidly.
Thick smoke filled the cockpit.
The aircraft had to be abandoned and it
was every man for himself.
>> [music]
>> Unpiloted now, the American bomber would
crash with all its bombs into the frozen
sea.
The base was alerted. They had to find
the men before they died of cold.
The local Inuits formed another team. At
its head, a Danish civilian in charge of
logistics, Jens Zinglersen.
>> We hear that it is a B-52 with nuclear
weapons that had crashed on the ice.
There was no way to get out there. The
fire trucks, they are constructed to
to to drive on a runway, and they cannot
drive on on on Arctic ice.
I get my dogs and my people ready. And
my theory was that our dogs would smell
and warn us and may help us to find
survivors even if they were unconscious.
While the Dane was rushing to the scene
of the crash, Thule's fire brigade
searched the area around the base for
survivors.
Marius Schmidt was their chief.
>> We found one of the pilots.
He was freezing.
His arm was really like ice.
Another had a broken leg.
But we found them all and took them to
the hospital.
>> After 10 hours out on the ice, Jens
Zinglersen got back to base. It had been
quite a feat to get to the crash site,
and he was keen to get to headquarters
to give his report to General Hansaker,
in charge of the accident.
But once there, he found a summit
meeting in progress.
>> And I came into a room where there was a
number of high-rank officers. So, they
were key a quick glance around.
And then in the middle sits here a
wild-looking, blue-eyed
two-star general with a face like a
Roman statue, arrogant, and he looks at
me sort of down his nose.
I said, "Okay, stranger, let me hear
your story." I reported short.
And then he looked at me and said, "God
damn it, I don't believe a word of your
story." And then he turned around
and
talked to his staff officers.
I felt really pissed.
A young captain came with a sort of a
meter.
So, I
put up my boot and he put his instrument
there and it went out of
And then he turned to the general and
said, "It's true. He has been out
there."
And then, suddenly, the whole atmosphere
changed.
>> Now, Strategic Air Command's war machine
was gearing up.
It was highly likely that the four bombs
had leaked radioactivity, twice as much
as at Palomares. Never before had there
been a nuclear accident like this one.
But, the US Air Force just wasn't
prepared to handle a catastrophe of this
amplitude, and President Johnson wanted
at all costs to avoid a diplomatic
crisis with Denmark.
>> Spain has allowed the Air Force to fly
nuclear weapons
above its soil.
Whereas in Greenland, controlled by the
Danes, the Danish did not approve
overflights with nuclear weapon.
>> Danish leaders knew that to handle this
crisis, they had to get on with their
American counterparts. However, it was
impossible to keep the accident secret
because they had thousands of people
working at [music] the base.
No one wanted to make the same mistakes
as at Palomares, so a press conference
was called straight away. This was a
first. The US military wasn't used to
this kind of communicativeness,
especially on such a thorny subject.
Jens Zinglersen enthralled the
journalists with his exploits out on the
ice. They'd come from all over the world
and knew nothing of life in the Arctic.
>> Very slow
down this
this area actually southeast.
>> But the man in charge, General
Hansicker, kept it brief.
>> How much is still in the ice?
I don't know. I haven't completed
our investigation.
How that's going to happen?
I don't know right now because I don't
know the extent of the contamination.
>> The press felt let down. Had they come
so far just for this?
>> And one small
>> But the aerial photography of the
gigantic black stain left by the B-52
spoke for itself.
A monstrous cocktail of burnt jet fuel
and radioactive material all frozen into
the ice.
When General Hansicker and his men went
to inspect this frozen swamp, they were
astonished to find nothing but tiny
pieces of the plane.
>> The aircraft and weapons hit with such a
force. The aircraft apparently at the
time was doing close to 700 miles an
hour
way above its design limits, but it did
hit the ice
more or less intact.
With all that destructive power
>> When it hit the 3-ft thick sheet of ice,
the aircraft had just disintegrated. As
for the bombs, who knew whether they'd
broken up, too?
One thing was sure, some of them must
have broken up. Just look at the
contamination.
Hundreds of employees at the base were
roped in to collect all the debris
scattered over dozens of square meters
of the Arctic landscape.
No one told them about the danger of
radioactivity.
>> They had Geiger measures and they found
some very hot spots. I saw instruments
reading
over 2 million counts per minute.
>> That's a huge dose, well above the
permitted limits even for a brief
exposure.
Further off, they discovered larger
fragments.
Were they from the bombs?
Experts had to examine them all one by
one to [music] determine their function
and their origin.
They were looking for clues like the
serial numbers inscribed on every
component.
And thus, three bombs were identified
with no room for doubt. That much is
confirmed by the declassified documents.
But there was no trace of the fourth
one.
By the beginning of March, nearly all
the debris had been recovered. Time for
for cleanup.
The experts said they had 2 months to
clean up the ice before it starts to
thaw.
They carefully outlined the contaminated
zone. It covered nearly 2 and 1/2 square
miles.
>> It was a huge
dispersal of radioactive material there.
As they could track the wind pattern to
where
everything that had been blown up in the
air had traveled down that wind pattern.
And they knew where it was.
And the Air Force there ended up feeling
efforts
remove the top 6 in of the ice and snow.
Huge quantities.
>> In just 60 days, they skimmed off over
10,000 tons of ice. Never had the Arctic
seen such a vast undertaking.
The contaminated ice was stored back at
the base in some old tanks.
>> The year goes on, the sun comes up, and
it gets full, and some of the tanks were
leaking. They were old tanks, they were
leaking, and [music] the contaminated
snow inside the tanks turns into water.
It leaks out. It has to be handled maybe
two or three times, moved from one tank
to another.
This is where
Danes have had a chance to be
uh contaminated.
>> The workers were the most exposed. They
had to be checked each day.
>> They checked us with the Geiger counter.
They burned all our clothes.
We couldn't keep them.
They came to the barracks.
They put cotton buds up my nose.
We were so stupid.
When the thing buzzed, we just laughed.
We were so ignorant. We didn't even know
what was happening.
That's me on the right with the cat.
Those are all Danish firemen and
Americans [music] posing in front of the
barracks there.
A lot of the Danish workers there
developed illnesses from the
radioactivity.
A lot of them died, sometimes very
young.
They created an association to try to
get compensation. Each one of them got a
lump sum of 7,000 euros from the
government.
Nothing from the Americans, not a dime.
The survivors didn't have any illusions
about the upcoming anniversary of the
accident.
What will you do for the 50th?
There won't be any more than 50 of us.
We're going to eat and drink, of course.
And then we'll stop.
Because we've had enough.
For us who were there,
just saying the name Thule makes us feel
nauseous.
In 1968, once they cleared up all the
ice, the Americans came up with a secret
plan.
>> In the summer 1968,
to get a submarine that could operate
below 200 m.
A tool they would never have done that
unless that it was important to them.
>> A declassified document from the Atomic
Energy Commission shows that the US Air
Force was still looking for the fourth
bomb.
>> [music]
>> For weeks and weeks, they were combing
the bay. And to their surprise, they
found that there was an area covered
with metallic debris.
They could prove from photos taken by
the submarine that it all did indeed
come from the B-52.
Bits of the fuselage and the landing
gear had sunk when it crashed.
So, why didn't the famous lost bomb?
The mission was cut short without
finding it.
And they gave up trying.
>> My theory is that it will it has been
released from
its hold inside the airplane, gone
through the
uh gone through the ice and sank to the
bottom.
>> What's still down there in the water?
Each of these bombs contained over 2 lb
of plutonium. Is that poisonous relic of
the Cold War still lurking down at the
bottom of the North Star Bay?
Thule was the 30th nuclear accident in
less than 20 years. But faced with a
Soviet threat, the strategists kept on
insisting that the B-52s should keep on
flying their deadly rounds.
President Johnson knew what he wanted,
for the US to turn towards using
missiles instead.
But they too caused their share of
catastrophes. It would take another 20
years to put an end to the Cold War.
For the bombers, there would be no more
warning missions. Their long reign was
at an end.
By the spring of '68, both the
superpowers had international troubles.
A wind of change was blowing.
>> [applause]
>> For the Soviet Union, it was a wake-up
call. Their empire was breaking up. In
Czechoslovakia, Russian tanks put an end
to all the hopes of the Prague Spring.
But all over the Eastern Bloc, the
thirst for democracy was growing.
In the United States, it was the Vietnam
War that was changing hearts and minds.
A war for freedom, supported by the
American people, had turned into an
imperialist adventure.
And defeat was already in sight.
Everywhere, the young generation was
rising up against the old order. They
saw the Cold War, for their elders, a
necessary evil, as a threat to the whole
human race.
They were dreaming of freedom and love.
Maybe it was just a dream.
The nuclear weapons weren't going to
just disappear. But for the time being,
the young just wanted some peace.
>> Glorious
sunshine.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Glorious sunshine.